Guide to the Kuntu Repertory Theatre Records, 1973-2013 CTC.2015.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kuntu Repertory Theatre Records
1973-2013
c. 1947-2013
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kuntu Repertory Theatre
CTC.2015.01
61 Linear Feet (61 boxes, 41 oversized folders)
The Kuntu Repertory Theatre was founded in 1974 by Dr. Vernell Lillie and Robert Lee "Rob" Penny. For over 35 years, Kuntu was the predominant African-American performing arts group in Pittsburgh. The group produced over 100 mainstage plays, touring productions, workshops, classes, and special events before it ceased operations in 2013. These records contain materials related to the administration of the Theatre, theatrical productions, photographs, and audio and video recordings. NOTE: ONLY THE PRODUCTION RECORDS AND PHOTOGRAPHS IN THE COLLECTION ARE FULLY PROCESSED AND AVAILABLE FOR RESEARCH AT THE PRESENT; ADDITIONAL TIME IS NEEDED TO INCORPORATE SUBJECT FILES, ELECTRONIC RECORDS, ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS, WORKSHOP MATERIALS, ART AND MEMORABILIA, AND AUDIO/VIDEO MATERIALS.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Accruals
Additional material forthcoming.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kuntu Repertory Theatre Board of Directors and the Lillie Family in 2015.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into the following series:
Series I. Production Records, c.1947-2013
Series II. Subject Files (forthcoming)
Series III. Workshops, Classes, Events (forthcoming)
Series IV. Audio/Visual Recordings (forthcoming)
Series V. Photographs, 1975-2011
Series VI. Administrative Records
Series VII. Memorabilia and Artwork (forthcoming)
Series VIII. Electronic Records (forthcoming)
Biographical / Historical
The Kuntu Repertory Theatre (Kuntu) was founded in 1974 by Dr. Vernell Lillie and Robert Lee "Rob" Penny. For over 35 years, Kuntu was an African-American performing arts group in Pittsburgh. With roots in the Black Arts Movement, Kuntu provided a platform for Black artists and technicians to examine African-American experiences with the goal of creating personal growth and social change. The group produced over 100 mainstage plays, in addition to touring productions, workshops, classes, and special events before it ceased operations in 2013.
The Theatre's philosophy was rooted in the concept of Kuntu drama. "Kuntu" is a Bantu word meaning mode or way. It follows the cultural traditions of the African continuum in which the art experience, rather than the art object, are vital. Kuntu and Dr. Lillie were influenced by and were contemporaries of scholars of Kuntu Drama and African philosophy such as Paul Carter Harrison, Oliver Jackson, and Janheinz Jahn. Kuntu selected plays that stressed elements such as a coexistence of humor and seriousness, a sense of community without a single protagonist and antagonist, preacher rhythms that elicit call-and-response from the audience, ancestral worship, the indivdual development to the extent of their capacity for the benefit of the group, and rituals and traditions that flow from the African consciousness.
The founding artists of Kuntu Repertory Theatre were Dr. Vernell Lillie (1931-2020), Professor Emeritus in the University of Pittsburgh Africana Studies Department, as Artistic Director; playwright August Wilson (1945-2005) as acting coach on some early productions; and Rob Penny (1941-2003) as Playwright-in-Residence. Wilson and Penny, also known as Oba Kilonfe, began Kuntu Writers Workshop with poet Maisha Baton (1938-2009), who led the workshops in children's literature. Other contributors to Kuntu include Eileen Morris, Bob Gore, Ken Ellis, and Marta Effinger-Crichlow. Kuntu became nationally recognized for its development of celebrated playwrights and produced plays by Dr. Lillie, James Baldwin, Kathleen Collins, Lorraine Hansberry, writer/actor Chadwick Boseman, Valerie Lawrence, and William Mayfield, among others.
In 1975, Kuntu debuted with a production of Little Willie Armstrong Jones by Rob Penny at Pitt's Stephen Foster Memorial Building. Lillie directed Homecoming in 1976, the first August Wilson play to be produced by a resident theater company. In addition to producing thirty-seven annual mainstage seasons, Kuntu performed a collage touring production of scenes and monologues from the Black Arts canon, created by Dr. Lillie. They also toured internationally, conducted psychodrama classes in schools, jails, and senior citizens' centers, and sponsored local community events.
Stephen Foster Memorial theater, located on the University of Pittsburgh Oakland campus, was the primary performance space for Kuntu's mainstage performances. Later, regular venues included the Masonic Temple, later Alumni Hall, and the Homewood branch of the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh system.
While Kuntu Repertory Theatre was a community-based theatre, it was also a departmental activity and special project of the Black Studies Department, later the Africana Studies Department. In addition to students, faculty, and staff, membership included other dedicated individuals living in the greater Pittsburgh area. However, around 2010, Kuntu became a registered 501(c)3 non-profit organization separate from the University of Pittsburgh.
Sponsorship Note
The processing of the audio/visual media in this collection was supported by a Recordings at Risk grant from the Council on Library and Information Resources. The grant program is made possible by funding from The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.
Related Materials
Alliance for Progressive Action Records, 1990-2003, AIS.2004.15, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
August Wilson Archive, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Black Action Society Files, 1968-1992, UA.55.13.3, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Community Media, Inc. Records, 1989-2003, AIS.2004.01
Ford E. and Harriet R. Curtis Theatre Collection of Pittsburgh Theatre Programs, 1840-present, CTC.1966.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Kuntu magazine. Archives Service Center - University Archives RG 90/8/44-B FF 4 Library has v.2: no.1 (1980:Nov.) and v.3 (1981:Nov.)
Lillie, Vernell, University of Pittsburgh Personal Files, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Penny, Rob, University of Pittsburgh Personal Files, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Tim Stevens Papers, 1945-2006, AIS.2006.11, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System (Kuntu Theatre spots for B-PEP, 1991 (tape 6))
Schools- Arts and Sciences- Black Studies Department, University of Pittsburgh Archives Information Files, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Scope and Contents
The Kuntu Repertory Theatre Records contain artistic and administrative materials created by members of the Kuntu Repertory Theatre from its founding in 1974 through 2013. Records were created as part of the operations of the Theatre first as a project of the Africana Studies Department at the University of Pittsburgh and later as a 501(c)3 organization to produce performances and conduct workshops. Some materials document the activities of other local arts organizations and community groups. These materials were pulled from a donation from the Board of the Kuntu Repertory Theatre and a donation of materials from the family of Dr. Vernell Lillie. Dr. Lillie's faculty papers have been separated into its own collection.
Types of materials include scripts, newspaper clippings, production programs, rehearsal schedules, set designs, lighting designs, costume designs, posters, photographs, constitutions and by-laws, newsletters, grant proposals, reports, marketing materials, meeting minutes, correspondence, sheet music, audio and video recordings, and digital records.
African American theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Repertory theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; College theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; American drama -- African American authors -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Scripts (Documents); Theater programs; Administrative records; Clippings (Information artifacts); Sheet music; Photographs; Sound recordings; Videotapes; Kuntu Repertory Theatre; University of Pittsburgh. Department of Black Studies; University of Pittsburgh. Department of Africana Studies; Lillie, Vernell A. (Vernell Audrey), 1931-; Penny, Rob; Kuntu Writers Workshop
- Production Records, c. 1947-2013; I.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records documenting the Kuntu Repertory Theatre's productions, whether they be mainstage dramatic performances, touring shows, or special performances. Records are arranged chronologically by season or alphabetically by title of show or event. A typical Kuntu season ran from September-August.
  - Clippings and Press, 1974-2012; 1.
    This subseries contains newspapers, magazine clippings, printed online articles, and photocopies that document Kuntu Repertory Theatre's activities, especially performances. Types of press include performance reviews, interviews, as well as event listings and advertisements in local publications. These include the New Pittsburgh Courier, Pittsburgh Renaissance News, Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, The Pitt News, The Pittsburgh City Paper and others. This subseries is arranged chronologically by date of publication. Oversize clippings have been housed separately.
    - Clippings and Press, 1974-1975
    - Clippings and Press, 1976
    - Clippings and Press, 1977
    - Clippings and Press, 1978
    - Clippings and Press, 1979
    - Clippings and Press, 1980
    - Clippings and Press, 1981
    - Clippings and Press, 1982
    - Clippings and Press, 1983
    - Clippings and Press, 1984
    - Clippings and Press, 1985
    - Clippings and Press, 1986
    - Clippings and Press, Ma Rainey's Black Bottom, 1987
    - Clippings and Press, 1987
    - Clippings and Press, 1988
    - Clippings and Press, 1989
    - Clippings and Press, 1990
    - Clippings and Press, 1991
    - Clippings and Press, 1992
    - Clippings and Press, Article on Dr. Lillie in Pittsburgh Magazine, 1993
    - Clippings and Press, 1993
    - Clippings and Press, 1994
    - Clippings and Press, 1995
    - Clippings and Press, Articles related to Killin' and Chillin' in the Hood, 1996
    - Clippings and Press, Articles related to Traces, 1996
    - Clippings and Press, 1996
    - Clippings and Press, 1997
    - Clippings and Press, 1998
    - Clippings and Press, 1999
    - Clippings and Press, 2000
    - Clippings and Press, 2001
    - Clippings and Press, Articles related to Whispers to Holler, 2002
    - Clippings and Press, 2002
    - Clippings and Press, 2003
    - Clippings and Press, 2004
    - Clippings and Press, 2005
    - Clippings and Press, 2006
    - Clippings and Press, 2007
    - Clippings and Press, 2008
    - Clippings and Press, 2009
    - Clippings and Press, 2010
    - Clippings and Press, 2011
    - Clippings and Press, 2012
    - Clippings and Press, Undated
  - Music, 1991-2011; 2.
    This subseries contains published and unpublished sheet music and song lyrics. Some sheet music includes handwritten annotations. This section is arranged chronologically by season, then alphabetically by production, when known. The end of subseries includes music from Kuntu-sponsored performances and unidentified productions, arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Season 1991-1992, Union Station, sheet music
    - Season 1992-1993, Crawford Grill Presents Billie Holiday, sheet music
    - Season 1993-1994, Evolution of Jazz, sheet music
    - Season 1997-1998, Tambourines to Glory, sheet music
    - Season 1998-1999, Sacred Ground, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Bubblin' Brown Sugar, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Bubblin' Brown Sugar, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Bubblin' Brown Sugar, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Bubblin' Brown Sugar, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Bubblin' Brown Sugar, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, vocal book
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music (Mapcase 27-1, Oversize 1)
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music (Mapcase 27-1, Oversize 2)
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music (Mapcase 27-1, Oversize 3)
    - Season 2004-2005, Jelly's Last Jam, sheet music (Mapcase 27-1, Oversize 4)
    - Season 2004-2005, Sophisticated Ladies, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Sophisticated Ladies, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Sophisticated Ladies, sheet music
    - Season 2004-2005, Sophisticated Ladies, sheet music
    - Season 2007-2008, Ain't Misbehavin', sheet music
    - Season 2007-2008, Ain't Misbehavin', sheet music
    - Season 2007-2008, Ain't Misbehavin', sheet music
    - Season 2007-2008, Journey of the Spirits, sheet music
    - Season 2008-2009, Among the Best, sheet music
    - Season 2008-2009, Clean Drums, sheet music
    - Season 2008-2009, Clean Drums, sheet music
    - Season 2009-2010, Raisin, sheet music
    - Season 2009-2010, Raisin, sheet music
    - Season 2009-2010, Raisin, sheet music
    - Season 2009-2010, Raisin, sheet music
    - Season 2009-2010, Raisin, sheet music
    - Season 2010-2011, Mahalia Jackson, sheet music
    - Season 2010-2011, Mahalia Jackson, sheet music
    - The Book of American Negro Spirituals, sheet music, Undated
    - Christmas performances, sheet music, Undated
    - I Am a Black Woman, song lyrics, 2000
    - Poems and song lyrics, Undated
    - Press, publicity, and artist info for Billy Harper, c. 1994-2002
    - Senior performances sheet music and song lyrics, c. 2002
    - A-H, sheet music, Undated
    - I-R, sheet music, Undated
    - S-W, sheet music, Undated
  - Posters, 1975-2013; 3.
    This subseries contains printed and hand drawn posters used to advertise specific Kuntu Repertory Theatre performances, seasons, and events. Posters are arranged chronologically by season, then by specific performance, when known. Those posters that advertise special events or activities are grouped together at the end of the series. Oversize posters have been housed separately.
    - Season 1975-1976
    - Season 1976-1977
    - Season 1981-1982
    - Season 1982-1983
    - Season 1983-1984
    - Season 1984-1985
    - Season 1985-1986
    - Season 1986-1987
    - Season 1987-1988
    - Season 1988-1989
    - Season 1991-1992
    - Season 1993-1994
    - Season 1994-1995
    - Season 1995-1996
    - Season 1996-1997
    - Season 1997-1998
    - Season 1998-1999
    - Season 1999-2000
    - Season 2000-2001
    - Season 2001-2002
    - Season 2002-2003
    - Season 2003-2004
    - Season 2004-2005
    - Season 2005-2006
    - Season 2006-2007
    - Season 2007-2008
    - Season 2008-2009
    - Season 2009-2010
    - Season 2010-2011
    - Season 2011-2012
    - Season 2012-2013
    - Posters for events featuring or presented by Kuntu Repertory Theatre, 1995-2002, Undated (Mapcase 27-1, Oversize 5)
    - Poster for Seven Guitars, 2006 (Mapcase 27-1)
    - Posters for Associated Acts, Events, and Conferences, c. 1980-2004; 11 x 14 inches - 12 x 18 inches (Mapcase 27-5, Oversize 2)
    - Posters for Associated Acts, Events, and Conferences, 1980-2004; 14 x 22 inches - 18 x 24 inches (Mapcase 27-5, Oversize 3)
  - Programs and Flyers, 1974-2013; 4.
    These records are arranged by date and season. Records include seasonal programs, individual show programs, general Kuntu Repertory Theatre informational brochures, flyers for individual shows, flyers for seasons, and flyers for ticket sales. Some performances have their own folders, this includes programs from the Edinburgh Fringe Festival from 1989 and 1994, a Summer Youth Company performance in 1977, and the "Miss Black Teenage Beauty Pageant," featuring Victory L. Bowser Collins from 2000.
    - General Promotional Materials, 1990-2010
    - Programs, 1974-1975
    - Programs, 1975-1976
    - Programs, 1976-1977
    - Programs, Kuntu Reperatory Theatre Summer Youth Company, 1977
    - Programs, 1977-1978
    - Programs, 1978-1979
    - Programs, 1979-1980
    - Programs, 1980-1981
    - Programs, 1981-1982
    - Programs, 1982-1983
    - Programs, 1983-1984
    - Programs, 1984-1985
    - Programs, 1985-1986
    - Programs, 1986-1987
    - Programs, 1987-1988
    - Programs, 1988-1989
    - Programs, Edinburgh Fringe Festival, 1989
    - Programs, 1989-1990
    - Programs, 1990-1991
    - Programs, 1991-1992
    - Programs, 1992-1993
    - Programs, 1993-1994
    - Programs, Edinburgh Fringe Festival, 1994
    - Programs, 1994-1995
    - Programs, 1995-1996
    - Programs, 1996-1997
    - Programs, 1997-1998
    - Programs, 1998-1999
    - Programs, 1999-2000
    - Programs, "Miss Black Teenage Beauty Pageant" Ft. Victory L. Bowser-Collins, 2000
    - Programs, 2000-2001
    - Programs, 2001-2002
    - Programs, 2002-2003
    - Programs, 2003-2004
    - Programs, 2004-2005
    - Programs, 2005-2006
    - Programs, 2006-2007
    - Programs, 2007-2008
    - Programs, 2008-2009
    - Programs, 2009-2010
    - Programs, 2010-2011
    - Programs, 2011-2012
    - Programs, 2012-2013
    - Publicity, 1974-1975
    - Publicity, 1975-1976
    - Publicity, 1976-1977
    - Publicity, 1977-1978
    - Publicity, 1978-1979
    - Publicity, 1979-1980
    - Publicity, 1980-1981
    - Publicity, 1981-1982
    - Publicity, 1982-1983
    - Publicity, 1983-1984
    - Publicity, 1984-1985
    - Publicity, 1985-1986
    - Publicity, 1986-1987
    - Publicity, 1987-1988
    - Publicity, 1988-1989
    - Publicity, 1989-1990
    - Publicity, 1990-1991
    - Publicity, 1991-1992
    - Publicity, 1992-1993
    - Publicity, 1993-1994
    - Publicity, 1994-1995
    - Publicity, 1995-1996
    - Publicity, 1996-1997
    - Publicity, 1997-1998
    - Publicity, 1998-1999
    - Publicity, 1999-2000
    - Publicity, 2000-2001
    - Publicity, 2001-2002
    - Publicity, 2002-2003
    - Publicity, 2003-2004
    - Publicity, 2004-2005
    - Publicity, 2005-2006
    - Publicity, 2006-2007
    - Publicity, 2007-2008
    - Publicity, 2008-2009
    - Publicity, 2009-2010
    - Publicity, 2010-2011
    - Publicity, 2011-2012
    - Publicity, 2012-2013
    - Programs and Publicity Presented by Kuntu, 1985-2010
    - Programs and Publicity Co-Sponsored by Kuntu, Dramatic Reenactment of Computer Room Takeover, c. 1993
    - Programs and Publicity Co-Sponsored by Kuntu, Hittite Empire, 1994-1995
    - Programs and Publicity, Undated
    - Programs and Publicity, Undated
    - Programs and Publicity Kuntu Associated Acts, 1974-1985
      This folder contains programs and flyers for performances of plays by Rob Penny, Javon Johnson, and other Kuntu members performed by theatres other than the Kuntu Repertory Theatre. It also includes programs featuring the Afro-American Dance Center, Bob Gore, and Linda Wharton.
    - Programs and Publicity Kuntu Associated Acts, 1986-2003, Undated
    - Programs and Publicity Kuntu Associated Acts, Paul Robeson: A Two Act Play with Don Marshall and Bob Gore, 1988
    - Promotional materials, 1996, 2001 (Mapcase 27-5, Oversize 1)
  - Scripts and Promptbooks, c. 1947-2011; 5.
    This subseries contains performed and unperformed scripts and promptbooks. This was determined by reviewing production programs and flyers in the collection. Some materials may not have been used in performances, and some scripts might not be the official ones used by actors or crew members, but they were maintained by the Theatre for review, reference, or were produced as part of the Kuntu Writers Workshop. Some plays were performed multiple times throughout the years, which is noted in the repeating show titles. All works are ordered alphabetically by title into the sections "Performed" and "Not Performed."
    - Performed
      - African Quilt: A Kuntu Collage arranged by Benjamin Blakey and Marcial L. Jones, Undated
      - Africana Reflections: The Past is Prologue arranged by Vernell A. Lillie, 1992, Undated
      - Ain't Misbehavin' by Richard Maltby Jr. and Murray Horwitz, Undated
      - The Amen Corner by James Baldwin, Undated
      - Among the Best: The Pittsburgh Crawfords and Homestead Grays by Rob Penny, 1992-2009, Undated
      - Ashes to Africa by Austin Sills, 1999
      - Ashes to Africa by Mark Clayton Southers, 1999-2003
      - Ashes to Africa no author listed, Undated
      - Black Pittsburghers by Rob Penny, 1993-1994
      - Black Women Speak of Womanhood arranged by Vernell A. Lillie, 1973
      - Blues for an Alabama Sky by Pearl Cleage, 1996, Undated
      - Blues in Jazz Waters arranged by Vernell A. Lillie, 1998, Undated
      - Blues on the Cross by Rob Penny, 1981, Undated
      - Boppin' with the Ancestors by Rob Penny, 1994
      - The Brothers by Kathleen Collins, 1982
      - Bubbling Brown Sugar by Loften Mitchell, 1985, 2005
      - Buffalo Soldiers: Plus One by Vernell A. Lillie and Ernest McCarty, 2003-2004
      - Cells by Vinnie Rizzo, c. 2000
      - A Civil Divorce author not listed, Undated
      - Clean Drums by Rob Penny, 1991
      - Computer Room Takeover (damatic reenactment) by Sybil Berry, Undated
      - The Conjure-Man Dies by Rudolf Fisher, 2000
      - Contribution by Ted Shine, c. 1970
      - Binder Pt. 1, Contribution, Slam the Door Softly, Depths of Her Star, c. 1977; Includes Kuntu meeting and directing workshop
      - Binder Pt. 2, Community Kitchen, Question Mark on Her Face, The Homecoming, c. 1977
      - Binder Pt. 3, The Homecoming, Wine in the Wilderness, Question Mark on Her Face, c. 1977
      - Crawford Grill Presents Billie Holiday by Vernell A. Lillie, 1989-2003, Undated
      - Crawford Grill Presents Billie Holiday and Mahalia Jackson by Vernell A. Lillie, 2003
      - Cryin' Shame by Javon Johnson, 1999
      - Dark Cowgirls and Prairie Queens by Linda Parris-Bailey, 1983
      - Deadwood Dick, Legend of the West by W.B. Burdine Jr., 1976-2004
      - The Death of Bessie Smith by Edward Albee and In White America by Martin Duberman, 1959, 1963
      - Depths of Her Star by Rob Penny, c. 1976
      - Diane's Heart by Rob Penny, 1976
      - Binder Pt. 1, Season 2008-2009, Diane's Heart, Clean Drums, Undated
      - Binder Pt. 2, Season 2008-2009, Pain in My Heart & Reachings, Undated
      - Binder Pt. 3, Season 2008-2009, Among the Best, Undated
      - Diane's Heart Dries Out Still More by Rob Penny, 1976-1977, Undated
      - Difficult Days Ahead in a Blaze by Rob Penny, 2001-2002
      - The Dilemma of a Ghost by Ama Ata Aidoo, Undated
      - Do Lord Remember Me by James de Jongh, 1977-c.1985
      - Donald Henderson: A Man of Letters and a Real Brother author not listed, 1993
      - Dowry by Elie Kihonia, c. 2001
      - Dutchman and The Slave by Leroi Jones, c. 2009
      - Eighth Day of the Week by Prester Pickett, 1995-2001
      - El Hajj Malik by N.R. Davidson Jr., Undated
      - The Evolution of Jazz: From the Fields to the Urban Night Clubs concieved by Vernell A. Lillie and arranged by Marta J. Effinger, 1994-1996, Undated
      - Flyin' West by Pearl Cleage, c. 1996
      - Fortunes of the Moor by Barbara and Carlton Molette, 1995-1999
      - Freeman by Philip Hayes Dean, c. 1973-1979
      - Good Black Don't Crack by Rob Penny, 1972-2005, Undated
      - Good Black Don't Crack (segments) by Rob Penny, 1972-2009, Undated